<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="file:/Z:/Documents/CEI_TEIP5/tei_cei/out/tei_cei.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><TEI xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cei="http://www.monasterium.net/NS/cei"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Title</title><editor>illuminierteurkunden@gmail.com</editor><principal><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1726-1712" xml:id="gv"><forename>Georg</forename><surname>Vogeler</surname></persName></principal><respStmt><resp>Project Lead; Art historical description</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9503-7097" xml:id="mr"><forename>Martin</forename><surname>Roland</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Art historical description</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8406-0785" xml:id="gb"><forename>Gabriele</forename><surname>Bartz</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Diplomatic description</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3269-453X" xml:id="mg"><forename>Markus</forename><surname>Gneiß</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Project Lead; Diplomatic description</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1967-6022" xml:id="az"><forename>Andreas</forename><surname>Zajic</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Digital transformation; modelling</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5114-0594" xml:id="sw"><forename>Sean</forename><surname>Winslow</surname></persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Digital transformation</resp><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0594-1902" xml:id="mb"><forename>Martina</forename><surname>Bürgermeister</surname></persName></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="https://www.fwf.ac.at/"><choice><expan>Fonds zur Förderung der wissenschaftlichen
                                        Forschung</expan><abbr>FWF</abbr></choice></orgName> Projekt P 26706-G21 "Illuminierten Urkunden als
                            Gesamtkunstwerk" and Projekt FWF-ORD84 "Erhalt fachspezifischer
                            Funktionalitäten bei Langzeitarchivierung in einem allgemeinen
                            Datenarchiv für die Geisteswissenschaften."</funder></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher><orgName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1137284463" corresp="https://informationsmodellierung.uni-graz.at">Zentrum für
                                Informationsmodellierung - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities,
                                Karl-Franzens-Universität Graz</orgName></publisher><distributor><orgName ref="https://gams.uni-graz.at">GAMS - Geisteswissenschaftliches
                                Asset Management System</orgName></distributor><availability><p>All texts and pictures are protected according to national copyrights
                                and exploitation rights. Furthermore, all rights of publication and
                                duplication of the pictorial reproductions of the documents are held
                                by the respective archive’s proprietor. Any means of publication is
                                therefore bound to above mentioned authorization and infringement is
                                punishable.</p><p>We would like to make all users aware that addresses, time and
                                duration of access will be stored on our server. The place of
                                jurisdiction for all disputes arising from this agreement is the
                                court nearest to the respective archive.</p><p>Conditions of use of printed editions and depictions apply in the
                                same way to scientific utilization. Citation according to good
                                scientific practice is therefore expected. (URL, author,
                                archive)</p><p>When publishing or duplicating research results (including
                                unpublished theses and dissertations) obtained from data provided by
                                Monasterium.Net, we would like to ask every user to pass a free
                                sample copy to the respective holder of the originals (archive).</p></availability><pubPlace>Graz</pubPlace><date>2018-10-25T06:51:55.661Z</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><listWit><witness><msDesc><msIdentifier><altIdentifier resp="https://illuminierte-urkunden.uni-graz.at/"><idno>1429-05-12_unbekannt</idno></altIdentifier></msIdentifier><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><material>Pergament</material><dimensions/></support><condition/></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc><diploDesc><copyStatus type="original">Original</copyStatus><listBibl type="other"><bibl/></listBibl><listBibl type="edition"><bibl/></listBibl><listBibl type="regest"><bibl/></listBibl><bibl/><listBibl type="unknown"><bibl/></listBibl><p>Arenga: <foreign>Quamquam regiam Romanam munificenciam cum sole deceat cottidie relucere et iugiter aliquid agere quomodo regalis nominis gloria possit attolli, illud tamen thezauris eius signanter apponitur, per quod personis providis circumspectionis industria et morum honestate predictis honor impenditur et digna meritorum premia tribuuntur.</foreign></p><p><quote><date>die duodecima mensis maii.</date></quote></p><issued><placeName>Bratislava (<foreign>Posonii</foreign>)</placeName><date when="14290512">1429-05-12</date></issued></diploDesc><authDesc>Siegel abgefallen</authDesc></msDesc></witness></listWit></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>The <ref target="https://illuminierte-urkunden.uni-graz.at">Illuminierte
                                Urkunden</ref> project is a cross-disciplinary historical,
                            art-historical, and digital humanities project which collects illuminated
                            medieval charters from all over Europe, publishes them, and explores
                            them in detailed studies.</p></projectDesc></encodingDesc><profileDesc><abstract><p><term ref="http://gams.uni-graz.at/skos/scheme/o:epis.2386#">Wappenbrief</term>: <legalActor type="issuer">König <persName>Sigismund</persName></legalActor> verleiht <legalActor type="recipient"><persName>János</persName></legalActor>, <legalActor type="recipient"><persName>Mátyás</persName></legalActor>, <legalActor type="recipient"><persName>András</persName></legalActor> und <legalActor type="recipient"><persName>Péter Kölkedi</persName></legalActor> ein Wappen.<legalActor type="issuer">König <persName>Sigismund</persName></legalActor> bestätigt, gibt erneut, verleiht und erteilt (<foreign>confirmamus et ea de novo damus, concedimus et ... elargimur</foreign>) mit wohlbedachtem Mut, gutem Rat seiner und des Heiligen Römischen Reichs Fürsten, Grafen, Edlen, Baronen und Adeligen und rechtem Wissen (<foreign>animo deliberato, sano principum, comitum, procerum, baronum et nobilum nostrorum et imperii sacri accedente consilio et de certa nostra sciencia</foreign>) den <foreign>nobilibus</foreign> Brüdern <legalActor type="recipient"><persName>János</persName></legalActor> (<foreign>Johanni</foreign>), <legalActor type="recipient"><persName>Mátyás</persName></legalActor> (<legalActor type="recipient"><persName>Matheo</persName></legalActor>), <legalActor type="recipient"><persName>András</persName></legalActor> (<foreign>Andree</foreign>) und <legalActor type="recipient"><persName>Péter</persName></legalActor> (<foreign>Petro</foreign>), den Söhnen des <persName>István Kölkedi</persName> (<foreign>Stephani de Kewlkede</foreign>), sowie allen Erben für die zahlreichen Verdienste und die vergangenen und künftigen treuen Dienste der Empfänger und ihrer Erben an König, Reich und dem Königreich Ungarn ein Wappen (<foreign>arma seu nobilitatis insignia</foreign>), das sie und ihre Vorfahren bereits in vielen Kämpfen (<foreign>per multa armorum curricula</foreign>) geführt haben, nämlich in blau und schwarz geteiltem Schild ein Adlerfang mit Krallen in verwechselten Farben mit durchgeschossenem Pfeil (<foreign>in campo bipartita coloris superius glauci, inferius vero nigri femur cum pede et ungula aquilei similitier bipartiti superius nigri, inferius glauci color cum sagitta transfixo ... ex inferiori parte pedis</foreign>), mit der Bedeutung, dass aus dem unteren Teil des Beins die Krallen der Demut und Tugend vom Pfeil der Versuchung und des Unglücks durchbohrt werden, durch die unabänderliche Kraft aus dem blauen Feld gestärkt werden und vom blau und schwarz geteilten Flug auf dem Helm die Erhabenheit der Tugend gestützt wird (<foreign>quam ex inferiori parte pedis quid pro ungula humilitatis et virtutis apprehenderitis, constanter teneatis et</foreign> [...] <foreign>sagitta temptationis et adversitatis percussi, aliqua ratione deficientes desperatione frangamini, sed magis ca</foreign>[rita]<foreign>tis soliditate firmati ex glauce campi robore inmutabiles perseveretis et ex galea alarum duplicitate splendidis nigri inferius et glauci coloris superius ad superna desideria quadam contemplatione subvecti evahamini ampliori virtutum eminentia fulciendi</foreign>), wie es in der Mitte der Urkunde farbig eingemalt ist (<foreign>in presentibus pictoris magisterio per figuras et specias congruas distinctius sunt</foreign>). Die Begünstigten dürfen das Wappen fortan nach der Art anderer waffentragender Adeliger (<foreign>more aliorum militatum nobilium</foreign>) in Kämpfen, Turnieren, Lanzenstechen und allen militärischen Übungen und auch sonst überall (<foreign>preliis, torneamentis, hastiludiis et generaliter in omni exercitio militari et aliis ubique locorum</foreign>) ungehindert führen. Er verbietet (<foreign>nolumus</foreign>), dass jemand durch die Bestimmungen der Urkunde (<foreign>per presentem armorum concessionem</foreign>) in der Führung ihrer eigenen Wappen behindert wird.<lb/>Daniel Maier</p></abstract><textClass><keywords scheme="Illurk-Urkundenart"><term ref="http://gams.uni-graz.at/skos/scheme/o:epis.2386#">Wappenbrief</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item><date when="2018-10-25">2018-10-25T06:51:55.661Z</date> Last
                                    checked by CAC</item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><facsimile><graphic url="http://images.monasterium.net/illum/IllUrk/1429-05-12_Sigismund-fuer-Koelkedi_DL-50521.jpg"/><graphic url="http://images.monasterium.net/illum/IllUrk/1429-05-12_Sigismund-fuer-Koelkedi_DL-50521_Deatil-Wappen.jpg"/></facsimile><text><body><div type="tenor"><p/></div></body></text></TEI>